Guide to the Alvin Seale Diaries, 1901-1940
Department of Special Collections
Alvin Seale Diaries,
1901-1940
Special Collections M0172
Seale, Alvin, 1871-1967.
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted access: requires 24 hour paging period.
Provenance
Gift of Mr. Elvis Frapwell, 1967.
Scope and Content
A collection of volumes of the diary of Alvin Seale and his wife Jessie recorded from 1901 to 1940. In the diary there are accounts of various parts of the world (e.g. Philippines, Hawaii, Hong Kong, South Seas, Galapagos, Latin America, U.S.A.). Most of the information recorded has to do directly with the place being visited, the biological activity in the area, and Seale's career as an Icthyologist. There are extensive notes on fish and bird specimins, many informative picutres, and a great deal of vivid narrations of his travels.
Information related to Stanford University and D.S. Jordan is included. There are accounts of Seales appointment to a fisheries post in the Philippines, work for the Steinhart Aquarium, and the San Francisco Aquarium. Also included are miscellaneous items and photographs dating from 1892 to 1956. Letters to Seale are in this section as well.
Biographical Note
ALVIN SEALE, 1871-19 67
A. B. Stanford: '96
Icthyologist, curator of fishes, Bishop Museum, Honolulu, 1901-4; assistant Smithsonian Institute and U.S. Bureau Fisheries, 1905; chief, Division of Fisheries; associate icthyologist, museum comparative zoology, Harward; Superintendent Steinhart Aquarium, Calif. Academy of Sciences, 1923-41, Emeritus Supt. since 1941. Participated in various expeditions to such places as Alaska, the South Pacific, New Zealand and Australia, Samoa, and the Far East. Author of Systematic Icthyology, Icthyology of the Pacific Islands, and Aquarium Building and Management.
Container List
- Diary 1901-1902.Fish and Bird specimens; archeology and anthropology sketches and maps; notes on birds; some plates, one dated 1914 or 1916,typed with MS corrections or variations. (Box 1, Folder 1.)
- Diary 1905-1915.Philippine Islands; Stanford University; Pickwick Club; Death of Mrs. Stanford; David Starr Jordan; Hawaii; Canada; New York and east coast; appointment to post in Philippines concerning fisheries; Anna Alexander's Expedition to Alaska for Berkeley Museum; Big Game; Earthquake in San Francisco `06;Stanford University; photographs of Philippine Islands, Hawaii. (Box 1, Folder 2.)
- In Distant Lands-- picture albumn, 1911.By Alvin and Ethel Seale: pictures taken shortly after wedding; Pacific Grove; Indiana; pictures of western states; Hongkong; Haight's saw mill; province of La Laguna. (Box 1, Folder 3.)
- Under Pine and Palm, 1911.Picture albumn: pictures of Alvin and Ethel Seale; the Anna Alexander expedition to Alaska 1906;Big Game; Indiana; Stanford University; Hawaiian Islands; Guam; Australia; Tahiti; Olive Rush. (Box 2, Folder 4.)
- Film Book. The Moro County, 1914,negatives identified, San Ramon Penal Colony--travel. (Box 2, Folder 5.)
- Diary 1929.Samoan Islands typescript--collecting fishes Steinhart Aquarium maps; photos; passengerp LIST; Hawaii, New Royal Hawaiian Hotel; crossing the equator; Pago Pago. Cousin: Alfred Seale of Palo Alto; interesting summaries; bibliography; photo of Evermann; envelope in back containing 1916passport; Many newspaper clippings. (Box 2, Folder 6.)
- Diary 1930,California. Photos of Alvin and Ethel Seale (1930)Diary (handwritten). Aquarium routing; cataloging library; I expect to leave these all to my alma mater Stanford University; Bob Prouty; Mariposa County; Dr. Herre; Crane Expedition; Swain Wilbur; Hoover; references to Stanford University and its people; Prohibition; recovery of Stanford Axe; New Zoo; postcards; David Starr Jordan; clip from Ripley's Believe It or Not; A Seale is superintendent of the S.F. Aquarium; W. Cameron Forbes telegram. (Box 3, Folder 7.)
- Diary 1931. Notes along the way, photos; postcards; programs; postcards; clips in envelope. (Box 3, Folder 8.)
- Diary 1931-2.G. Allen Hancock Expedition to Galapagos Islands; map; equator stamp; Diary typed list of members; photos; collecting species; Mexico; Panama; Canal Zone; Dr. Ritter; Cocos Is.; Nicaragua; lecture outline; radiogram news, etc., clips. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  5/17/32. ALS W.C. Forbes from Barrel P.O. Bay Galapagos
- Diary 1933.Trip to Salt Lake; Rough Log; Bum Town Sacramento; photos; William Beele; research on brine [UNK]; national affairs; wild flowers; Salt Lake; AAAS convention; Nevada; beginning of Bay Bridge, clips. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Diary 1934-8.Postcards; S.F. general strike; Reds; notes signed from J. Diviny, V.P. of Teamsters local 85; Crocker collection (fish); China Clipper, first airmail flight to Manila; motion picture of fish in color (1936)gift of and dedication Seale; South Sea library to Pacific Grove; clipping of Mr. Belloli. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Diary 1938.Note to Jessie. world trip typed; Japan, Hong Kong; signs of war; Philippines; Manila; visits several aquariums; Singapore; Penany; Ceylon; Bombay; Suez; Cairo; Naples; Aquarium; Rome, Interlaken; Frankfort; Berlin; Amsterdam; Brussels; Paris; London; Brighton; War Averter New York; Indiana; Chicago 1916passport signed H.L. Hershey; map of cruise. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Diary 1940.Air trip U.S. to Mexico; itinerary for air trip June 1;engagements; costs; New York Aquarium; St. Augustine Marineland, Mexico; Approaching Retirement, postcards and photos; some from earlier dates, including S.U. prior to 1906;construction of chapel; professors Julius Seminole; Stanford and Palo Alto 1892,etc., construction of Steinhart Aquarium; South Seas and Hawaii; Eclipse Expedition 1930;Aquarium Society outings; Stanford Univ. portrait of Seale. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Pacific Exploration and Voyages; hand copied maps; typed notes with ms corrections and additions re. earlier voyages. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- The Seale South Sea Library; lists 1292 vol. by author, publisher, date, and price. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Mis. pieces: (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - a. 24 June 1892commencement program of Fairmont Academy
  - b. 1930pic. of Patterson Family
  - c. 1931photo of Joseph Mailliard, Naturalist.
  - d. 1942photo of Alvin Seale
  - e. 1942, 25 Nov.Jacqueline Perry to A. Seale
  - f. 1942, 30 Dec.W.C. Forbes to A. Seale
  - g. 1943, 3 Jan.Alice Eastwood to A. Seale
  - h. 1943, 6 Jan.A.M. Alexander to A. Seale
  - i. 1944, 4 Apr.Edwin Bryan to A. Seale
  - j. 1941, Mar.Page of Diary
  - k. 1948, Oct.3 Pages of Diary
  - l. 1948, Nov.Pages of Diaries (Folder 5, Folder 16)
  - m. 1952, Apr. 15Lady-in-waiting of Queen Elizabeth II to A. Seale
- Misc. Pieces: (Folder 5, Folder 17)
  - a. 4 Feb. 1950Alice Eastwood to A. Seale
  - b. 19 July 1952Jose Montilla to Seale
  - c. 20 Nov. 1952Allan Hancock to Seale
  - d. Page from Diary, Nov. 22, 23. Jan. 24, 25, 1952.
  - e. Page Pic. Diary from Mar. 15 to 24, 1953.
  - f. Diary. Oct. 15-17, 1953.
  - g. 29 June 1954.Allan Hancock to Seale.
  - h. 21 July 1954M.F. Bettencourt.
  - i. Notice from Calif. Acad. of Sci. informing Seale of his election as Fellow 5, Oct. 1955.
  - j. 28 Nov. 1955Wm. Dennis to Seale
  - k. 29 Dec. 1955Robt. R. Harry to Seale
  - l. 23 Jan. 1956W. Cameron Forbes to Seale
- Misc. photos, undatedletters, pic. of D.S. Jordan, and Jock (His dog), poem Galapagos by Edwin O. Palmer. (Folder 5, Folder 18)